Guide to the Carl Lobozza Photograph Collection 1895-1896 PR 269
New-York Historical Society
Carl Lobozza Photograph Collection
1895-1896
New-York Historical Society
PR 269
0.21 Linear feet (1 box; 31 gelatin silver prints and 27 negatives)
The Carl Lobozza Photograph Collection spans the period from 1895 to 1896 and primarily contains photographs of Prospect Park, unidentified residences and portraits. Little is known about this collection. What information is known was taken from the photographer's notes, written on the negative sleeves. The collection appears to be taken by an amateur photographer and include snapshots from their daily life.
Provenance
Gift of Carl Lobozza, 1981.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Historical Note
The Kodak camera was marketed to the public in 1889. This invention, with its fixed-focus, as well as Kodak's photo-processing services, simplified photography. Shortly after, in 1890, celluloid film was created. It was lightweight and durable, replacing glass and paper based photography. These advances made photography more accessible to the general public, allowing anyone to be a photographer. The "snapshot" was born, with photographers capturing images of their daily lives, without formal training. These changes also helped to alter the way photography was viewed, increasing the divide between artistic photography and documentary images.
Scope and Content Note
The Carl Lobozza Photograph Collection spans the period from 1895 to 1896 and primarily contains photographs of Prospect Park, unidentified residences and portraits. Little is known about this collection. What information is known was taken from the photographer's notes, written on the negative sleeves. The collection appears to be taken by an amateur photographer and include snapshots from their daily life. Each negative is approximately 3 3/8 inches square and the photographs are contact prints made from these negatives. The collection is divided into two series by format: I. Photographs; II. Negatives.
Arrangement
Collection is divided into two series: Photographs; Negatives. Material in each series is arranged by subject.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Additional snapshots from this time period can be found in the Album File (PR 002), the Geographic File (PR 020), and the Portrait File (PR 052).
negatives (photographs); Photographic prints.; Gelatin silver prints.; Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Portraits.; Townsend, Dana; Townsend, Sue
- Series I: Photographs
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Photographs contains 31 photographs, some with labels such as "Burleigh," "Davis house interiors," and "Shore Road." There are also several unidentified buildings in both city and rural locations. The images of Prospect Park include bicycle riders, the lake, a "summerhouse," and a cow on the lawn.
  Portraits are either identified with a last name only or not identified at all, with the exception of two photographs one of "Sue" Townsend and the other if Dana Townsend. Both children are shown riding a bicycle on a city sidewalk. There are several duplicate prints throughout the collection.
  - Prospect Park, 1895 November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Shore Road [Brooklyn?], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified locations - Misc., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Burleigh, 1895 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Davis House Interiors, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Portraits, 1896, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Negatives
  Series II. Negatives include 27 original negatives from which each print was made. There is at least one print made for each negative, except one, a negative labeled "Summer lookout on Shore Road." Many of these negatives were numbered by the photographer.
  - Prospect Park, 1895 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Shore Road [Brooklyn?], undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified locations - Misc., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Burleigh, 1895 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Davis House Interiors, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Portraits, 1896, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)